I think it is more obvious than it has
ever been that we live in subjective
realities and Trump you know I don't
want to talk a lot about Trump but he's
he's clearly the person who most
exemplifies that the you could see what
I call the two movies playing on one
screen yeah that people are living in
completely different realities some
people are living in a some kind of a
horror movie in which everything's gonna
blow up any minute and others of us are
living in the Golden Age it's never been
better and it's not just because it's
better for some people it's worse for
others it's really the same kind of
people they just happen to have
different political views some see it as
a tragedy and some see it as a comedy
but they can both survive and reproduce
and work so one of the things we're
we're all learning at the same time and
that's what I write about is that you're
not seeing the world the way other
people are you're just not experiencing
the same thing they are and for all
practical purposes you live in your own
subjective world now that's independent
of whether there is a is a truth below
that we don't even we don't even have to
get to that the only thing we we know
for sure is that we don't have access to
it as humans so that that's an
interesting point it's sort of headed
off my next question at the pass a
little bit my last recording I did was
with an artificial intelligence expert a
PhD from MIT who's worked in the field
for a number of years his name is Nick
cos mattis and he's gonna be I'll
probably release his a little bit before
this one and I asked him a question
about you know computers and their
ability to you know perceived the world
visually and whether or not that was
going to lead us to conclude that there
was an actual concrete objective reality
that you know we can point to and say
yeah that rock is the rock and that's
all the things to it and look these
computers from my very different angle
are seeing it the same way to would that
at the end of the day to you know sort
of definitively show us that there is an
objective reality so that's my question
to you on that subject and then I guess
you've already told me that it doesn't
matter but well it might be true that
all robot
have the same subjective reality I mean
I can see that because you'd program
them they'd act they'd act in a
predictable way but if you said okay now
let's take my robot my artificial
intelligence and have it talked to the
two of us who disagree on the reality it
wouldn't work
you know even if you totally trusted
that the robot was seeing things
realistically you'd still think this
robot was broken if it disagreed with
you it's like well I see what you're
saying but I'm pretty sure this robots
defective because that's not what I'm
seeing so people don't really easily
change their minds about reality itself
but but really I'm talking about
interpretations of reality not not the
question of whether a rock is there or
not there we we generally agree on what
the rock is there or not there right do
you how much do you think our
perceptions of an objective reality and
our own subjective reality then is
influenced by our sort of our DNA and
sort of a biological determinism because
in your writing I definitely get the
sense that you mean very explicitly say
that the information that we absorb in
the language that we use the language
that we're given help shape our own
reality but at the same time I also
struggle with the notion that you know
for example you know can men and women
just switch their genders and their
sexuality is on a whim I don't I don't
know that that's true because I do
believe that there's an element of our
gender expression masculinity that's
tied to our biology and to who we are
chemically you know etc and so to what
extent are those forces working together
in opposition which one is stronger what
do I need to rely on more do I need to
rely on I'm changing the inputs that go
into my head or maximizing the outputs
that come out of my DNA what do you
think about that well in my how to fail
book I talk about humans as being voiced
robots in other words the the common way
that people imagine themselves and other
people is that you have thoughts and
then those thoughts translate into your
actions and and certainly that's you
know true ish that that does happen but
the hypnotist
you know and I'm a trained hypnotist and
when you learn the hypnosis you you
learn that the world is backwards or
upside down if you prefer and that what
really happens is that our body is
informing our brain what to think so you
can see that easily if you're let's say
you have kids and your kids are tired or
hungry you know they start fighting and
complaining and yelling and you can't
get them to do anything and then you
feed him a hot dog and then suddenly
they stop complaining they clean up
their room and the first time somebody
explained that to it was it was my
ex-wife she said no they're just hungry
and I would look at them and say that's
not just hungry there's something
there's something going on you know
deeply disturbing with these children
and then you feed them and then they
become normal immediately now of course
as an adult you've had that experience a
million times you know that if depending
on your state of mind the world can look
like a horror or a delight and and once
you learn that if you get your body
right if you take care of your health
your your stress especially you know get
to sleep diet exercise if you get that
stuff right then your brain starts
working the way you think you should
have before but if but if you just start
with the brain and said let me let me
think my way out of these bad thoughts
that's a that's a tough one yeah
interesting so if you took two people
who are watching them the screen and
seeing two different movies and you feed
them properly train them properly
exercise them give them enough sleep
make them as comfortable as possible is
that gonna get them closer to the same
movie or are they still gonna be seeing
two different movies if you can optimize
yourself you're still going to have
those differences yeah you're still
gonna have those differences the only
difference in that example you gave me
is that's people watching the scary
movie it might be less scared yeah yeah
because if your body is physically in
good shape
you can handle stress better so so that
would only be a minor correlation there
is it possible to get people just to
watch a different movie
I hear people who say that I have
changed them so I asked after the 2016
election I did a tweet in which I asked
people if anything I had done had
changed their vote or their opinion
about Trump as a candidate and I think
something like if I recall fifty and
hundred people told me that they changed
their entire political view because of
watching me now that's just how many
people responded Brian so you can
usually you know ten times that at the
minimum okay so I don't know maybe maybe
fifty hundred thousand people changed
their views after watching me but there
were probably people who did not have
super-hardened views so the people who
said you know let's say they were
conservative to begin with and their
first impression of Trump was negative
well they were still conservatives and
he was still promoting conservatives
views so it wasn't that big of a leap to
go from you know being conservative to
embracing Trump it would be really hard
to change somebody from Democrat to
Republican or vice versa
changing demo hey everybody that's my
dog Rosie hey Rosie my podcast listeners
an audience deaf whoa Rosie and just so
happens the mailman decided to come
right that's we're recording so Rosie
thank you honey I'll probably edit this
part out I don't usually I did anything
but maybe this part so that brings me to
another question is so if people well
first of all Democrats are deplorable is
kind of my whole shtick so that's that's
where my main focus has been on on
myself I went through a process of
abandoning the Democratic Party I voted
for Obama two times I probably voted for
Clinton if I can remember I never ever
voted Republican no one in my family
ever voted Republican but 2016 was was a
time in which I realized that the
Democratic Party had definitely moved
away from me and that the the the new
Republican Party as embodied by Trump
and some of other elements to it were
appealing to me and so maybe you know
maybe I didn't really change the party's
changed I think that that's one one
reasonable example but if we are
to watch two different movies and in
doing so watching those two different
movies leads us to conflict or when I
ask you what what are the consequences
of having a nation that can observe the
same thing and come away with to almost
terrifyingly different conclusions well
first of all it's not new so you have to
if you if you look at the super big
picture or the course of evolution over
the life of the earth look at all the
animals who don't understand their
reality you know does a clam understand
this reality does your dog understand
its reality really I mean it doesn't
know that the mailman is delivering mail
it just just thinks it's an intruder or
something right so apparently and and I
think we can say this safely because
they're just literally what tens of
thousands of examples and no counter
examples we can see all these creatures
who don't understand their reality
they're not humans but they don't
understand that and yet they could
reproduce they have they have everything
they need there's there's nothing
lacking if they can reproduce
that's all evolution demands of you so
what are the odds that humans have
evolved to finally get to the point
where they understand their reality and
you were lucky enough to be here for it
I mean 15 billion years of since the Big
Bang and how lucky that this little you
know hundred year period you just happen
to be born when we figured it all out so
I take it as given that we don't
understand a reality but the the the two
moviepro thing is not that different
from a lot of things we see that work
for example capitalism is you know buyer
and a seller each you're trying to get
it over on the other one it's you know
they're probably nine entertain ten
things fail in capitalism and yet
capitalism works even though it's is
built around primarily failing nine and
ten businesses that's a pretty big
failure rate and if you look at voting
and cap and democracy you know
democratic systems republic etc it's
full of conflict and lying
and and and fake news and it seems like
it's just this big cauldron of bile and
and evil and then we wake up in the
morning and we have the strongest
economy you know a super capable
military we're safer than we've ever
been and I'd have to say that the the
conflict that we see is largely a
theatrical construct meaning that
because politics is now our new form of
entertainment and the whole world is
watching you see essentially the
exaggerated a hyperbolic theatrical
version of reality and people you know
as a lifestyle they buy into one version
or another but there's something about
the way the system is designed let's
give all credit to the founders who came
up with the Constitution and yeah we've
tweaked it over time but if somehow
handles all of that conflict all of that
stupidity all of that selfishness all of
that fake news all that lying and
produces the Golden Age and we're at a
point where humans have never looked at
a better situation than we're looking at
right now absolutely so apparently it's
not a problem that needs to be solved
because think them at the the big
picture is things improve basically
every year yeah you know that is a
perspective I think that comes with age
when I have these conversations with my
mother no I'm 44 so I'm not young but
when I have these questions with my mom
she always takes those like 10 steps
back and she's like I has just been like
that forever and look where we are now
everything's gonna be just fine don't
you worry about it but then you know you
get focused on the minutia and you and
you experience like for example I went
to the Richmond Second Amendment gun
rally on January 20th and while I was
there everyone was super nice there was
a variety of different people diverse
groups of people were there everybody
had their guns out it was like it was
like one one-hundredth of rowdy as any
NFL football game you've ever been to
and it was just like a really lovely
pleasant day
and then the news reports that came out
of it we're just like look at all these
racists with their guns what if there
were black people there with guns what
would happen then we'll guess what there
were and they were and they took
pictures with them and everybody was
super cool and nice and so I left that
experience which I've had a number of
times my own personal life being called
a Nazi and getting fired for it even
though I was and you know obviously and
each of these times they still still
managed to you know cause us really
severe just I get incensed though a
little bit I've really agitated because
I feel like this is something that needs
to be resolved we need to be able to see
facts and and things the same way so
that we can come together we can do
happy but that's what you're you know
this what I'm saying yeah you're saying
no no they're all evidence suggests that
we don't need to agree on reality
because we have you know thousands of
years of civilization and which we
haven't we got this are I mean we made
it this far
with all of those flaws and it made no
difference at all now do you think
perhaps these circumstances are
different given the prevalence of social
media and Technology
I read her Aires or Harvey sapiens book
and in there he talks about how our
societies coalesced around him shared
imagined orders and then I read a bunch
of technologists and and and media
specialists today that talk about how in
the old days we had a top-down
information distribution system where
Walter Cronkite would tell us all what
to think and feel at night and we were
all unified and we had cohesion today
now because the liberation of
communication via technology we are not
talking one-to-many we're talking
many-to-many and therefore there's now a
million different imagine orders and now
we don't share in those imagined orders
in the way that we did and therefore
we're now seeing a breakdown in social
cohesion well any weight to that well I
would modify that by saying that we have
two dominant at least political views
you know there's the left and the right
and I've always said that people don't
form political opinions on their own
opinions are assigned to them by the
dominant media
now if you ask somebody they say well
it's my opinion but here's the tell it
always matches their preferred news
source always so you know you could take
almost any negative story about Trump
and say okay let's just try to imagine
that this had been reported as just the
facts would no opinion Laird on what
would you think about it and you would
find that almost everything that's
alarming and scary and you know
completely inappropriate and everything
else about Trump whatever whatever
complaint they're bringing today you
would find that almost all of it would
just go away if all you did is describe
what he did instead of having the
pundits come and say well what he was
thinking or or where this will lead us
to or what he really means but didn't
say it's all that stuff they divides us
it's not what he actually does right but
I think in this in this argument people
are talking about how it's not even
dominant news media that are creating
new narratives for us
for example our mutual friend Mike Serna
Mitch he's very successful at creating
media narratives and they of course
spread into larger institutions and then
people get it from there but there is an
element now I think of a you know we
were sort of like in a unipolar
communication world and now we're in
this multipolar world where everybody's
talking and there's nodes everywhere and
I I just wonder if it's not so easy to
dismiss this notion that failing to
maintain a shared imagined world order
or shared ideas of who we are in our
head because in America at least we're
very much our identity is based on a
shared idea rather than shared genetics
or shared bloodlines that in our
particular case especially since our
nation is one of ideas that if these
ideas are now multiple and diverse and
coming at you from all directions and
able to recruit you into smaller and
smaller teams that they may that may
have a long-term negative effect on
social cohesion that we have not yet
been seen before or or positive because
all this stuff is completely
unpredictable but what I said
what I see is it seems like it used to
be a question of you know you got your
Democrats against your Republicans then
of course you had the media that was a
big player but I think things because of
social media we now see a battle that
seems to be shaping up between two sides
one that has money and the other has
influence now now that you know both
sides have both some money and some
influence etc but people who were
skilled at influence you know they
actually have the tools to influence and
make sort of itches one I'm another if
we have a big enough audience we become
the people who create that shared
imagination yeah I don't mean just me
personally but people were influential
enough to have big audiences and you
know they're good with words and they
understand persuasion so they can you
know package their words just right it
makes things viral I mean if you look at
you know Jack pasaba k-- mics or in a
bitch you know or my Twitter you see
that all three of us can generate fairly
viral tweets at will yeah almost every
single day you know all three of us are
hitting at least one that gets a lot of
lot of retweets usually several so and
and I think that because we have
unlimited reach we are now competitive
with people of money and can buy a can
buy at the New York Times can buy the
Washington Post
can buy this their own channels of
influence I think it's becoming a fair
it's a fair fight now didn't used to be
well that's interesting
frame to put it in yes Jack was so
vaguely actually even late without Jack
and I are good friends I've known Jack
now for almost half a decade and he is
just one of the finest gentlemen that I
have met period in life and I have
nothing but great things to say about
Jack he's just a good man a family man
his wife is lovely and always loved
spending time with them but he has been
on fire lately his Twitter has just been
on fire and you're right he can fire
things out at will and generate massive
interest and spread stories and create
narratives and actually control the
legacy media
as if they were on the end of a string
and I wonder to what extent that that
reads that I mean they had the the
legacy media hates you guys and and and
and how much of that is out of jealousy
or fear and and I want to circle back
later to this idea of fear I feel like a
lot of us are motivated we're all
motivated seemingly by fear and so to
what extent is there backlash based on
fear or jealousy and if so and talking
to you about making predictions this is
gonna be fun but so how does that play
out over five or ten years if if things
continue on a trajectory slippery slope
just kidding a trajectory like this what
is that what what could happen when
people with money see their influence
slipping they don't like that well
they'll probably try to hire that people
who have influence so I would imagine
that they're gonna try to buy whatever
is working for the other team because
they can but they're gonna have to find
people who were not as independent as
the three people you just mentioned